本节我们看另一种加密
In this segment we are gonna look at
another form of encryption called
叫做微调加密。我将使用硬盘加密作为应用
tweakable encryption. I'm gonna motivate
tweakable encryption using disk encryption
来引入微调加密，我们还会看到硬盘加密
as an application and we'll see disk
encryption as yet another application for
作为另一个确定加密的应用。那么硬盘加密问题
deterministic encryption. So the disk
encryption problem is that we wanna
是指我们想加密硬盘上的扇区。比如说，
每个扇区是4KB长度，问题是
encrypt sectors on disk. Say each sector
is four kilobytes long and the problem is
没有空间来扩展。换句话说，如果扇区大小是4KB
that there is no space to expand. In other
words if the sector size is four kilobytes
那么密文大小也必须是严格的4KB
the cipher text size also has to be
exactly four kilobyte because there is
因为没有地方写多出来的位，如果密文比明文长的话
nowhere to write the extra bits if the
cipher text was bigger than the plaintext.
那么我们的目标是，构建一个不扩展的加密
And so our goal is basically to build a
non expanding encryption where the cipher
其密文长度严格等于明文长度
text size is identical exactly equal to
the plaintext size. So what does it mean
加密不能扩展是什么意思？
that encryption can't expand? Well,
technically we were saying, basically the
就是说，明文空间等于密文空间。那么
message space is equal to the cipher text
space. So the message space will be four
明文空间是4KB信息，密文空间也是4KB信息
kilobyte messages and the cipher text
space would be also four kilobyte
在这个情况下，很清楚，我们必须使用确定性的加密
messages. In this case clearly we have to
use deterministic encryption because if
因为如果加密是随机的，那么将没有空间来存储随机性
encryption was randomized there will be no
place to store the randomness. And similarly
类似地，我们没有空间来存储完整性，因为我们不能
扩展密文，也不能加完整性的位
we have no room for integrity, because we can't
expand the cipher text and add any
所以我们最多可以获得确定性的CPA安全性
integrity bits. So the most we can achieve
is deterministic CPA security and that's
这是我们的目标。现在实际上可以证明一个简单的引理
going to be our goal. Now it turns out
there's a really simple lemma to
就是说，如果给我一个确定性的CPA安全的密码
prove, that basically says if you give me
a deterministically CPA secure cipher
其明文空间等于密文空间，没有扩展
where the message space is equal to the
cipher text space, so no expansion, then in
事实上这个密码是个PRP。我们这里是说
fact the cipher is a PRP. So, really all
we're saying here is if we want no
如果我们希望没有一点扩展，我们唯一的加密选择是
expansion at all, our only option for
encrypting is what we called construction
上节中我们所说的二号机制。我们必须使用PRP加密
number two in the previous segment. Namely
we have to encrypt using a PRP. So, let's
那么我们来看，我们可以如何使用PRP进行加密。
我们把我们的硬盘
look at how we might encrypt using a
PRP. Well, we take our disk, and we break
分解成各个扇区。现在，如果我们使用PRP、
用同样的密钥来加密每一个扇区
it into sectors. And now, if we encrypted
every sector using a PRP under the same
我们要看确定性加密的标准问题
key, we kind of run into our standard
problem with deterministic encryption.
如果扇区1和扇区3正好有同样的明文
Namely, if sector one and sector three
happen to have the same plain text, then
那么解密后的扇区1等于解密后的扇区3
the encrypted sector one would be equal to
the encrypted sector three and the
攻击者就知道对应的明文是一样的
attacker would learn that the
corresponding plain texts are the same.
这是一个真实的问题，例如你的一些扇区是空的
Now this actually is a real problem for
example, if your, if some of your sectors
它们的数据都被设置为0，那么事实上
are empty you know they are all set to
zero then in fact the encrypted sectors
加密的扇区将是一样的，因此攻击者就会知道
would be identical and as a result the
attacker would know exactly which sectors
哪些硬盘上的哪些扇区是空的，哪些不是。
这就很成问题了
on your disk are empty and which sectors
are not. So this is actually quite
问题是，我们能做得更好吗？答案是肯定的
problematic and the question is, can we do
any better? And so the answer is yes, and
我们首先想到的方法是，为什么不对每个扇区，
使用不同的密钥来加密呢？
the first idea that comes to mind is well,
why don't we use a different key for every
那么大家可以看到，1号扇区使用1号密钥加密
sector? So you can see sector number one
gets encrypted with key one, sector number
2号扇区使用2号密钥加密，等等。。
two gets encrypted with key two and so on
and so forth. So now even if the content
即使1号扇区等于3号扇区，1号扇区的密文
of sector number one is equal to sector
number three the cipher text of sector one
也会与3号扇区不同，因为它们是用不同的密钥加密的
and sector three will be different because
they are encrypted under different keys.
这样就防止了我们之前讨论的信息泄漏
So this actually avoids the leakage that
we talked about before although I do want
虽然我很想指出，这个模式下也会有很多信息泄漏
to point out that there is still a little
bit of leakage with this mode. For example
例如，如果用户正好改变了1号扇区里的一位
if the user happened to change one bit in
sector one and then that sector gets
然后这个扇区被加密成了一个不同的密文。
所以这完全被篡改了
encrypted into a different cipher text. So
this will be garbled all completely,
因为这是一个伪随机置换，这个扇区将会。。
because this is a pseudo random
permutation, the sector will be-- even if
即使明文中的一位改变了，这个扇区也会被映射到
one bit of the plain text changes, the
sector will be just mapped to a completely
一个完全崭新的随机输出。但是，如果撤销了这个改变
new random output. However, if the user
then undoes the change, and reverts back
还原到原先的扇区，那么加密的扇区也会回到原先的状态
to the original sector, then the encrypted
sector will revert back to its original
攻击者可以知道，一个改变做出后又撤销了
state, and the attacker can tell that a
change was made and then reverted. So,
所以还是有一点信息泄漏的，但是这种信息泄漏
there's still a little bit of
information leakage. But that type of
如果不牺牲系统性能，我们无能为力
information leakage, there's really
nothing we can do without really
所以我们忽略这点，姑且认为是可接受的
sacrificing performance. So, we're just
going to ignore that and deem that
下一个问题是，现在大家发现，我们的硬盘
acceptable. So the next question is now
you realize our disks are actually getting
容量越来越大，有很多的扇区。这就意味着
pretty big and there are lots of sectors.
So this would mean that we are generating
我们这里要产生很多的密钥，不过当然，
我们不需要去存储所有的这些密钥
lots and lots of keys here, but of course
we don't have to store all these keys, we
我们可以使用一个伪随机函数生成这些密钥
can simply generate these keys using a
pseudo random function. So, the way this
这个工作的方法是，我们有一个主密钥叫做K
would work is we would have a master key
which we would call K. And then the sector
然后我记扇区号为T，各个扇区使用主密钥加密
number which I'm gonna denote by T is
gonna be encrypted using the master key.
解密的结果将是特定的扇区密钥
And the result of that encryption would be
the particular sector key, which I'll
我把它记为K_T。这步是安全的，因为
denote by K sub T. Now the reason this is
secured is again because the PRF is
PRF与随机函数不可区分，意味着
indistinguishable from our random
function, which means that basically if we
如果我们对这些扇区号1,2,3,4...,L
应用一个随机函数
apply a random function to these sector
numbers, one, two, three, four, up to L,
它们被映射到密钥空间里完全随机的元素
they basically get mapped to completely
random elements in the key space and as a
因此我们使用新的随机独立的密钥来加密每个扇区
result we are encrypting every sector
using a new random independent key. So
这是一个很好的机制，但是对于每个扇区
this is a fine construction, however
again, for every sector we would have to
我们都必须应用这个PRF。自然就有问题了，
我们能做得更好些吗？
apply this PRF. And so the natural
question is, can we do even better? And it
实际上我们可以。这就引入了微调分组密码的概念
turns out we can. And this introduces this
concept of a tweakable block cipher where
我们只需要一个主密钥
really what we want is basically to have
one master key. And we want this one
我们需要这个主密钥来推导很多PRP。
那么我们说过，一种方法是
master key to derive many, many,
many PRPs. So we said one way to do that
使用PRP数加密密钥K。不过我们将看到
is simply encrypt the key K using the PRP
number. But as we'll see, there's a more
有一个更有效率的方法。现在这个PRP数就是所谓的微调
efficient way to do that. Now this PRP
number is actually what's called a tweak,
这就引入了微调的概念，微调分组密码
and that introduces this concept of
tweakable, a tweakable block cipher. So in
在微调分组密码中，加密和解密算法
a tweakable block cipher, the encryption
and decryption algorithm basically, as
通常取密钥为输入，取微调为输入
usual, take a key as input, they take a
tweak as input. This capital T is what's
记微调空间为T。当然它们也取数据为输入
called the tweak space. And of course they
take the data as input and they output
输出集合X里的数据。有一个性质是，对每个微调空间里的微调
data in the set X. The property is such that for
every tweak in a tweak space in a random
对每个随机密钥，如果我们固定密钥和微调
key. Basically if we fix the key and the
tweak, then we end up with an invertible
那么我们会得到一个可逆的函数，集合X上的
一一映射的函数。因为密钥是随机的
function, a one to one function on the
set X. And because the key is random with
这个函数事实上与随机函数不可区分
the, the function is in fact
indistinguishable from random. In other
换句话说，对每个微调的设定，我们都有一个PRP
words, for every setting of the tweak, we
basically get a PRP, an independent PRP
一个X到X的独立PRP。如我所说，作为这个的应用
from X to X. And as I said, the
application for this is now we're going to
我们使用扇区号作为微调，这样一来每个扇区
use the sector number as the tweak, and as
a result, every sector is going to get its
都有它自己的独立的PRP。我们讲快点，更为精确地定义
own independent PRP. So let me very, very
quickly just define more precisely what is
安全的微调分组密码。如我们所说，有一个微调空间
a secure tweakable block cipher. So as we
said there's a tweak space. There's a key,
有一个微调空间和一个输入信息空间X。通常，我们定义
a tweak space and an input space X.
And as usual, we define our two
两个实验。在实验1中，我们选择一个
experiments. Here in experiment one what's
gonna happen is we are gonna choose a
真随机置换的集合。我们不仅仅只选一个置换
truly random set of permutations. So not
just one permutation we're gonna choose as
而是与微调数目一样多的置换。那么
大家注意到，这也为什么我们把这个设定为
many permutations as there are tweaks. So
you notice this is why we raise this to the
微调空间的大小。如果微调空间的大小是5
size of the tweak space. If the size of
the tweak space is five, this says we are
那么我们选择5个集合X上的随机置换
choosing five random permutations on the
set X. And in the other case, basically,
我们将选择一个随机密钥，我们定义我们的置换集合
we're just gonna, you know, choose a
random key, and we're gonna define our set
根据微调空间里的微调来定义
of permutations as the ones defined by
the, by tweaks in the tweak space. And
然后攻击者提交一个微调和一个X
then the adversary basically gets to
submit a tweak and an X. And he gets to
他将看到由微调T1定义的置换在点X1处的值
see the value of the permutation defined
by the tweak T1, evaluated at the point
攻击者会一次又一次地看到这些
X1. And he gets to see this again and
again. And again, he gets to see the value
他将看到由微调T2定义的置换在点X2处的值
of the permutation defined by the tweak
T2, evaluated at the point X2, and so on
等等。。那么攻击者的目标是，分辨出他是在与
and so forth. And then his goal is to say
whether he interacted with truly random
真随机置换交互，还是与伪随机置换交互。
如果攻击者不能做到正确分辨
permutations, or pseudo random
permutations. And if he can't do it, we
我们就是这个微调分组密码是安全的。
那么它与常规的分组密码的区别是
say that this tweakable block cipher is
secure. So the difference from a regular
在常规分组密码中，你只能与一个置换进行互动
block cipher, is, in a regular block
cipher, you only get to interact with one
那么你的目标是，分辨出你是在与一个
permutation. And then your goal is to tell
whether you're interacting with a
伪随机置换交互，还是在和一个真随机置换交互
pseudorandom permutation or a truly random
permutation. Here you get to interact with
而这里你是在和|T|个随机置换交互。你的目标是
区分这|T|个随机置换
T random permutations. And again your goal
is to tell whether the T random
是真是伪。通常说，如果你不能区分
permutations are truly random or
pseudorandom. So as usual if you can't
如果攻击者在这两个实验中表现相同
distinguish, if the adversary behaves the
same in both experiments, we say that this
我们说这个PRP是一个安全的微调PRP。很好。
那我们来看几个例子
PRP is a secure tweakable PRP. Okay. Very
good. So let's look at some examples. So
我们已经看了这个简单的例子。在这个简单例子中
we already looked at, at the trivial
example. In the trivial example, what we do,
我们假设密钥空间等于输入信息空间
we just, we're gonna assume that the key
space is equal to the input space. So this
这个PRP将X乘X映射到X。以AES为例子
PRP really acts on, you know, X times X to
X. So think of AES for example, where
密钥空间128位，数据空间128位，当然
the key space is 128 bits, the data space
is 128 bits and of course the output is
输出空间也是128位，那么我们定义一个微调分组密码为
128 bits and then the way that we defined a
tweakable block cipher again there is a
有一个密钥、一个微调和待加密的输入数据
key, a tweak and data as input is
basically we encrypt the tweak using our
使用微调和主密钥，然后我们使用得到的随机密钥加密数据
master key and then we encrypt the data
using the resulting random key. Now
现在大家发现，如果我们想使用这个
微调分组密码来加密n个分组
you realize that if we wanted to encrypt n
blocks with this tweakable block cipher,
会要求2n次分组密码的计算：n次用于加密
this would require 2n evaluations of
the block cipher: n evaluations to encrypt
给定的微调，另外n次用于加密给定的数据
the given tweaks, and then n more evaluations
to encrypt the actual given data.
那么，我想给大家看一个很好的例子，
说明了我们实际上可以做得更好
So, I want to show you a nice example,
that shows that we can actually do better.
这个例子叫做XTS机制。它其实是起源于
This is called the XTS construction.
It's actually originally based on
Phil Rogaway的XEX模式。它如下工作
a mode called XEX due to Phil Rogaway.
And it works as follows. So suppose you
假设给我一个常规的定义在n位分组上的分组密码
give me a, a regular block cipher that
operates on n-bit blocks. So not a
不是微调分组密码，只是一个常规的分组密码
tweakable block cipher, just a regular
block cipher. We're gonna define a
我们来定义一个微调分组密码。这个微调分组密码
tweakable block cipher. So again, this
tweakable block cipher is gonna take two
取两个密钥作为输入，为求简便，大家待会将看到
keys as input. The tweak space, for
convenience, which you're gonna see in
我们假设这个微调空间由两个值组成
just a minute, we're gonna assume this
tweak space is made up of, of two values,
T和I。T是某个微调值，我们待会将讨论它
T and I. T is going to be some, you know, some
tweak value which we'll see in a minute, and I is
I是某个索引。然后X是n位字符串
going to be some index. And then X is
going to be an n-bit string which we're
我们将用微调分组密码加密X。那么XTS如下工作
going to apply the tweakable block cipher
to. So, the way XTS works is as follows.
首先我们加密微调T的左半部分
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to encrypt the left half of the
使用密钥K2。我们把加密的结果记为N
tweak, namely T, using the key K2 and we're
going to call the result N. So now what
接下来我们把信息m和某个密码本函数
we're gonna do is we're gonna XOR the
message m with some padding function
在我们刚刚得到的N处的值进行异或，索引是I
applied to this value N that we just
derived, at the index I. And this padding
这个密码本函数函数极快。我们大可以忽略它的运行时间
function is extremely fast. We can pretty
much ignore it in the running time. The
接下来我们要使用密钥K2加密，然后再进行异或
next thing we do is we're gonna encrypt
using the key k2. And then we're going
使用同样的密码本。我们使用这个密码本N来进行异或
to XOR again, using the same pad. So
we're going to XOR again using the pad
应用到索引I。得到的结果就是密文了，我们记为C
of N applied to I. And the result is going
to be the cipher text, which we'll denote
好，如我所说，这个函数P非常简单
by C. Okay, so again as I said, the
function P is some very, very simple
仅仅是某些有限域上的乘法，这里我就不解释了
function. It's just some multiplication in
a finite field which I'm not going to
非常之快，运行时间取决于
explain here. Very, very fast so the
running time is dominated by the running
分组密码E的运行时间。这就是XTS。
这个机制的好处在于
time of the block cipher E and that's it. That's
XTS. And the nice thing about this construction
如果我们想加密n+1个分组，我们只需要计算N一次
is now if we wanted to encrypt n plus one
blocks, all we do is we compute the value
然后对索引1,2,3,4，对每个分组
N once. And then for the indices one, two,
three, four basically we just need to
我们只需要计算PRP E一次。所以我们需要加密n个分组
evaluate the PRP E once per block. So we
would need to encrypt n blocks using the
使用T_1, T_2, T_3, T_4等等。我们只需要n+1次
tweaks T,1, T,2, T,3, T,4 and so on. We
would just need n plus one evaluations of
分组密码E的计算。所以这比简单机制要快出一倍
the block cipher E. So it's twice
as fast as the trivial construction.
所以我想让大家研究一会这个XTS机制
So I want you to stare for just a minute
at this XTS construction. So my question
我给大家的问题是，真的有必要在用微调前加密它吗？
to you is, is it really necessary to
encrypt the tweak before using it?
就是说，下面这个机制是安全的微调PRP吗？
That is, that is the following construction
a secure tweakable PRP. So you can see
在这个机制中，这个微调被直接使用，
作为这个密码本函数的输入
in this construction, this tweak is used
directly as input to the padding function
再异或，我给大家的问题是，如果我们这样做
for the XOR and my question to you is
if we did that, would that be a
这是一个安全的微调PRP吗？我再提醒一下大家，这是密钥
secure tweakable PRP? And let me
remind you again that, this is the key,
这是微调，这是数据
this is the tweak and this is the data.
我希望大家都认为这是正确答案
I hope everybody said that this is the correct answer.
如果我们把数据设为P(t,1)，然后把它
Basically, if we set the data to
be P(t, 1), then when we XOR it with the
和对应的微调进行异或，对应的微调也是P(t,1)。
所以我们得到的是0
corresponding tweak, which is also P(t,1)
we're gonna get here, zero. And so
所以我们加密的就是0，无论输出什么
what's gonna get encrypted is actually
zero, so whatever that comes out to be.
我们记输出为某值C0。那么实际输出为
Let's say that some value, C0. And
then the actual output is just gonna be C0
C0异或P(t,1)。现在我们对P(t,2)做同样的事情
XOR P(t,1). Now when we do the same
thing with P(t, 2), we're gonna get c0
我们会获得C0异或P(t,2)。然后我们把这两者异或起来
我们就会得到P(t,1)异或P(t,2)
XOR P(t, 2). And when we XOR these two
things together, we just get P(t, 1) XOR P(t, 2).
事实上这意味着攻击者可以询问挑战者
So the fact that this is true means
that an attacker can simply query the
以这个微调和这个数据
challenger at this tweak and this data,
this tweak and that data. And then just
然后计算挑战者的两个回复的异或，然后
比较合适的密码本函数值的异或
compute the XOR of the two responses, and
compare to the XOR of the appropriate
如果这个等式成立，我们是在与一个伪随机函数交互
padding values. And if the equality holds,
we're interacting with a pseudorandom
否则我们是在与一个真随机函数交互
function; otherwise we're interacting with
a, with a truly random function. So this
那么这就让攻击者能以优势1击败这个机制
would allow the attacker to defeat this
construction with advantage one. So just
总结一下，XTS用于硬盘加密
to summarize the way XTS is used for disk
encryption. What we do is we look at
我们看扇区号T，然后把扇区分成若干分组，
每个分组16字节
sector number T, and we break it into
blocks, sixteen byte blocks. And then
然后1号分组使用微调T1加密，
2号分组使用微调T2加密
block number one gets encrypted with a
tweak, T1. Block number two gets encrypted
等等。。这样每个分组都有其自己的PRP
with a tweak, T2, and so on and so forth.
And so every block gets its own PRP. And
这样整个扇区被加密了
the whole sector, as a result, is
encrypted, using, you know, a collection
使用一系列PRP。大家注意到，这是一个分组级别的
PRP，不是扇区级别的PRP
of PRPs. Now you notice, this is a block
level PRP. It's not a sector level PRP.
事实上，并不是每个扇区都用它自己的PRP加密的
So, in fact, it's not true that each
sector gets encrypted with its own PRP.
只是每个分组是用它自己的PRP加密的
It's just each block gets encrypted with
its own PRP. The distinction between a
扇区与分组之间的差别某种意义上是人为的。
实际上，这个XTS模式
sector and a block is some, somewhat
artificial, and this XTS mode actually
提供了扇区级的确定性的CPA安全的加密
provides you know, deterministic CPA
encryption at the block level, at the
(这里少讲了一个安全secure)
16字节的粒度。这是目标。这个模式实际上
16-byte level. That's the goal. And this
mode actually is fairly popular in disk
在硬盘加密的产品中很是流行。我写了几个例子
encryption products. I just wrote a couple
of examples here that actually support
它们支持XTS。那么我想告诉大家，在实际中
XTS. So I wanted you to know that this is
in fact how disk encryption is commonly
硬盘加密是如何实现的。那么总结一下，
微调加密是一个有用的概念
done in practice. So, to summarize,
tweakable encryption is a useful concept
当你需要许多从单个密钥推出的独立的PRP
to know when you need many independent
PRPs all derived from a single key. One
要记住的要点是，事实上这个简单的机制
important thing to remember is, in fact,
the trivial construction is not the most
不是最有效的。有更有效的机制，比如XTS
efficient. There are constructions like
XTS are actually more efficient, where you
你可以一个微调来重复使用加密，不同的微调
can kind of reuse encryptions from one
tweak to get many encryptions for many
可以获得许多不同的加密。所以这些是更好的方法
different tweaks. And so those are the
better ways to use them. Both the trivial
这个简单的机制和XTS机制都是所谓的窄分组机制
construction and the XTS construction are
what are called narrow block constructions.
它们为一个16字节的分组提供了微调分组密码
Namely they provide a tweakable block
ciphers for a sixteen byte block. But as we
但让我们所说，上一节我们看了EME机制
said, we looked the, at the EME
construction in the last segment, which
它提供了能处理长得多的分组的PRP。
事实上，EME是一个微调的操作模式
provided a PRP for larger, much larger
blocks and in fact EME is a tweakable
所以，如果大家需要能处理更长的分组的PRP
或是更长的分组的微调的PRP
mode of operation. So, if you need PRPs for larger
blocks or tweakable PRPs for larger
那么大家就使用EME。但大家注意在EME中
blocks then you would just use EME. But you
notice there, in EME, you had to apply the
每个输入分组必须应用分组密码两次，因此
它比XTS慢一倍
block cipher twice per input block, and
as a result it's twice as slow as
因此不是很常用。关于微调加密，这些就是我想说的
XTS, and is not very often used. So that's
what I wanted to say about tweakable
下节我们讨论保格式加密
encryption. And in the next segment we'll
talk about format preserving encryption.